Bilaal Ahmad

FRONTEND DEVELOPER

PROFILE

A reliable team player with experience in providing high standards of customer service in a professional environment.

Proficient in HTML, CSS, JavaScript & React, with a growing knowledge of backend web technologies.

Excellent logical thinking and problemsolving skills. Highly adaptable, and able to pick up new systems quickly and competently.

Aiming to develop new skills, whilst building on existing abilities obtained during my studies and employment.

PERSONAL DETAILS

Address

80 Northleigh Road Manchester Firswood M16 0EQ

CONTACT

- bilaal-ahmad@hotmail.co.uk
- 07568 461 389
- bilaal-ahmad.netlify.app
- Bilaal Ahmad
- Bilaal96

EXPERIENCE

E-commerce Web App - Crown Clothing

PERSONAL PROJECT | VIEW MY ONLINE PORTFOLIO IN CONTACT SECTION

May 2020 - April 2021

- Built a fictional online clothing store using industry-standard development tools; such as VS Code
- Learned as I built the app, requiring consistent practice, initiative & attention to detail
- Created reusable & composable components using the React library, including hooks
- Implemented Route-based Code Splitting to optimise component load times; using React Router Dom, React Suspense & Lazy (with dynamic imports)
- Used the Redux state-management library to maintain a single data store, as well as the Reselect package to memoize selectors for efficiency with derived data
- Explored render cycles, used React Devtools' Profiler tab to measure performance, and reduced unnecessary renders with React.memo, useMemo & useCallback hooks
- Mobile-first approach; used Styled Components to create a responsive web app with custom styles
- Used the Firebase SDK for user authentication & real-time data storage with Firestore
- Integration with Stripe using React and a simple Node.js & Express API utilising environment variables & middlewares
- Hosted the app using the Heroku platform

Sales Assistant

CIGTRONICA, MANCHESTER ARNDALE CENTRE

September 2017 - July 2019

- Required flexibility, attention to detail and excellent communication skills to handle a variety of different tasks
- Assisting customers and dealing with customer enquiries and complaints
- Cashier processing transactions, cashing up, checking daily float, occasionally viewing audit rolls
- Keeping up-to-date and familiarising myself with new products
- Conducting stock checks and placing orders for products Processing and overlooking weekly deliveries
- Working under pressure (e.g. Summer, Christmas & Black Friday Sales)
- Working towards store targets and keeping track of store Key Performance Indicators (such as inventory to sales ratios, customer satisfaction & customer retention)
- Trusted to open and close the store
- Housekeeping general cleaning, preparing the shop for the next day

Joomla Web Developer - Work Placement

ERNEST BENTLEY, FALLOWFIELD

March 2016 - July 2016

- Worked with a team member to design a trial website for Ernest Bentley (a builder's merchant). The trial assisted their decision in whether the business was ready to go online**
- Consulting with the clients in regularly held meetings, where swift decision-making, advice and guidance was provided
- Setup a Content Management System (CMS) for the clients to update the website with.
- Taught the clients how to use the CMS
- Setup social media accounts and taught the clients how to use them as marketing tools
- · Adjusting the website after client meetings, and presenting the changes made by an agreed deadline
- Development tools included: Joomla CMS & extensions, HTML5, CSS and a little JavaScript

EDUCATION

 BSc (Hons) IT with Business Technologies SHEFFIELD HALLAM UNIVERSITY

Awarded - 2:1

September 2014 - July 2017

SOFT SKILLS

Verbal & Written Communication

Efficient Time Management

Critical Thinking

Strong Work Ethic

MY DEVELOPER TOOLBOX



INTERESTS

Running, skipping & weight training

Science & Tech - from Software Development, Robotics, Astronomy & Space Travel

Self-taught in guitar playing; and I dabble in playing the keyboard

Reading - Fiction, Biographies, Productivity



Computer Hardware and Gaming, to Psychology,

^{**}The company decided that going online was a task of greater magnitude and risk (as a traditional brickand-mortar business) than they anticipated and have halted online progression.